Guide to the Basil Lee Whitener Papers, 1889-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Subject Series, 1953-1968,primarily 1961-1968
  - Ward, Truman, 1963-1966and undated (Box 165, Folder 3)
  - Wong Wa Ngen, 1961-1966 (Box 165, Folder 4)
- Case File Series, 1950-1962,primarily 1957-1960
  Although this series is very similar to the Subject Series in that it contains folders on miscellaneous topics, the two series were evidently separate in Whitener's office. There was no consistent order to the folders, so they have been arranged alphabetically, similarly to the Subject Series. Some folder title revisions were necessary. A particularly large section of this series is the three boxes of material from the National Federation of Independent Business containing ballots by businessmen on various issues. Some routine Items such as individual Veterans Administration and social security claims, as well as passport applications were discarded.
  - Agricultural Act (of1958), 1958 (Box 166, Folder 1)
  - Agriculture, 1956-1958 (Box 166, Folder 2)
  - Air Force Facility in Melvin Hill, N.C., 1958 (Box 166, Folder 3)
  - Area Redevelopment Act (S. 3683), 1958 (Box 166, Folder 4)
  - Belmont Abbey College, 1956-1960 (Box 166, Folder 5)
  - Blue Ridge Parkway, 1958 (Box 166, Folder 6)
  - Celo, N.C., 1957 (Box 166, Folder 7)
  - Census of1960, 1958-1960 (Box 166, Folder 8)
  - Cherry, Robert Gregg, 1957 (Box 166, Folder 9)
    Clippings concerning the death of Cherry, a former Governor of North Carolina.
  - Cleveland County, N.C., Election,1958 (Box 166, Folder 10)
  - Corps of Engineers, 1957 (Box 166, Folder 11)
  - Cotton (Long Staple), 1958-1959 (Box 166, Folder 12-13)
  - Cotton Acreage and Transfer Bill (H.R. 7740), 1959 (Box 167, Folder 1)
  - Cotton Acreage in Cleveland County, N.C., 1956-1957 (Box 167, Folder 2)
  - Cotton Acreage in Rutherford County, N.C., 1957 (Box 167, Folder 3)
  - Dalton, Arnold K., 1958-1959 (Box 167, Folder 4)
  - Democratic Congressional Dinner,1960 (Box 167, Folder 5)
  - Democratic County Organizations,1958 (Box 167, Folder 6)
  - Dorn Bill (H.R. 11250), 1958 (Box 167, Folder 7)
  - Duke Power Company, 1958-1960 (Box 167, Folder 8)
  - Duke University Ambassadors, 1958 (Box 167, Folder 9)
  - Elections,1958Consists of clippings. (Box 167, Folder 10)
  - Ervin, Ray E., 1960 (Box 167, Folder 11)
  - Excise Tax on Telephone Services, 1959 (Box 167, Folder 12)
  - Fair Trade Bill (H.R. 1253), 1959 (Box 167, Folder 13)
  - Federal Aid Highway Act of1959(H.R. 8678)1959 (Box 167, Folder 14)
  - Federal Crop Insurance, 1953-1959 (Box 168, Folder 1)
  - Federal Housing Administration, 1957-1958 (Box 168, Folder 2)
  - Fiber Industries, Inc., 1959 (Box 168, Folder 3)
  - Fish and Wildlife Service, 1957 (Box 168, Folder 4)
  - Foreign Aid, 1960-1962 (Box 168, Folder 5)
  - Caston County, N.C. Election,1958 (Box 168, Folder 6)
  - Hannah Harrison School, 1959 (Box 168, Folder 7)
  - Housing and Home Finance Agency, 1957-1958 (Box 168, Folder 8)
  - Immigration, 1952-1957 (Box 168, Folder 9)
  - Jontza, Guido, 1956-1959 (Box 168, Folder 10)
  - Kissing Incident, 1959 (Box 168, Folder 11)
  - Loyalty Oath (National Defense Education Act), 1960 (Box 168, Folder 12)
  - Luncheon in Forest City, N.C., 1959 (Box 168, Folder 13)
  - McDowell County, N.C. Election,1958 (Box 168, Folder 14)
  - Madison County, N.C. Election,1958 (Box 168, Folder 15)
  - Maleic Hydrazide (MH-30), 1960-1961 (Box 168, Folder 16)
  - Medical Society of the State of North Carolina, 1959 (Box 168, Folder 17)
  - Mica, 1958 (Box 168, Folder 18)
  - Minimum Wage, 1959 (Box 168, Folder 19)
  - Municipal Elections, 1959 (Box 168, Folder 20)
    Copies of congratulatory letters from Whitener to North Carolina mayors, city council members, and other elected officials.
  - National Debt, 1957-1958 (Box 168, Folder 21)
  - National Federation of Independent Business
    - Papers, 1957-1958,Aug. (Box 169, Folder 1-5)
    - Papers, 1958, Sept. - 1960 (Box 170, Folder 1-6)
    - Papers,1961 (Box 171, Folder 1-2)
  - Loose Ballots (Box 171, Folder 3-4)
    Ballots by businessmen on various issues, such as the closed shops, government loans, and social security.
  - National Park Service, 1959 (Box 171, Folder 5)
  - National Rivers and Harbors Congress, 1957 (Box 171, Folder 6)
  - News Releases and Congressional Record Insertions, 1957-1961and undated (Box 171, Folder 7)
  - North Carolina Oil Jobbers Association, 1959 (Box 172, Folder 1)
  - Polk County, N.C. Election,1958 (Box 172, Folder 2)
  - Post Office Department Complaints, 1958-1959 (Box 172, Folder 3)
  - Pre-fabricated House, 1958 (Box 172, Folder 4)
  - Pyramid Electric Company, 1957-1958 (Box 172, Folder 5)
  - Reciprocal Trade, 1960 (Box 172, Folder 6)
  - Rutherford County, N.C. Election,1958 (Box 172, Folder 7)
  - Sampson Master Switch Company, 1959 (Box 172, Folder 8)
  - Small Business Financing, 1958-1960 (Box 172, Folder 9)
  - Teener Baseball Team, 1960 (Box 172, Folder 10)
  - Textile Fiber Products Identification Act, 1958-1960 (Box 172, Folder 11)
  - Tobacco (Burley), 1958-1960 (Box 172, Folder 12)
  - Tobacco Warehouse, Burnsville, N.C., 1959 (Box 172, Folder 13)
  - U.S. Congress, 1950-1957 (Box 172, Folder 14)
  - Veterans Administration Office in Gastonia, N.C., 1957 (Box 172, Folder 15)
  - Veterans Pension Bills (H.R. 1181 and H.R. 6432), 1959 (Box 172, Folder 16)
  - Wage and Hour Law, 1957-1959 (Box 172, Folder 17)
  - Watershed Protection Project in McDowell County, N,C., 1958-1959 (Box 172, Folder 18)
  - Yancey County, N.C. Election,1958 (Box 172, Folder 19)
- Textile Imports Series, 1955-1968
  This series reflects the serious concern of Whitener and his constituents relating to textile imports and related issues such as foreign imports, cotton, the health of the textile industry, and tariffs. There is some material pertaining to legislation, especially for H.R. 6196, a bill designed to boost the cotton industry. There is some overlapping of similar topics among the various folders. The two major files in this series are Legislative Bills and Subject Files.
  - Legislative Bills
    - 85th Congress, 1st Session, 1957
      - H.R. 5691 To regulate the foreign commerce of the United States by establishing import quotas under specified conditions, and for other purposes. (Box 173, Folder 1)
    - 88th Congress, 1st Session, 1963
      - H.R. 2000 To amend the Agricultural Act of1956,concerning two-price cotton. (Box 173, Folder 2-5)
      - H.R. 6196 To encourage increased consumption of cotton, to maintain the income of cotton producers, to provide a special research program designed to lower costs of production, and for other purposes. (Box 174, Folder 1-4)
  - Subject Files
    - Cotton, 1956-1965and undated (Box 175, Folder 1-4)
      Miscellaneous papers concerning one-price and two-price cotton, etc. Included is alarge volume, dated September, 1962, which is a report to the President by the U.S. Tariff Commission on the topic of cotton products.
    - Cotton Equalization Case, 1961-1962and undated (Box 175, Folder 5-6)
      Pertains to an investigation and hearing before the U.S. Tariff Commission in late 1961 and 1962.
    - General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) (Box 175, Folder 7)
      Conference, 1959-1960 and undated Concerns a proposed concurrent resolution on tariffs.
    - Glove Imports, 1966 (Box 176, Folder 1)
    - Imports
      - Papers, 1961-1963; 1966-1967,Sept. (Box 176, Folder 2-5)
      - Papers, 1967, Oct. - 1968and undated (Box 177, Folder 1-4)
    - Japan, 1955-1960 (Box 177, Folder 5)
      Concerns Japanese textiles, imports, and tariffs.
    - Speech Material, 1961-1962and undated (Box 177A, Folder 1-2)
      Includes textile imports information.
    - Tariff Commission Hearing,1960 (Box 177A, Folder 3)
      Material pertaining to Investigation No. 22-22 under Section 22 of the Agricultural Adjustment Act, as amended, concerning articles containing cotton.
    - Textile Imports, 1961-1963and undated (Box 178, Folder 1-4)
    - Textile List,1962 (Box 178, Folder 5)
      Lists of textile companies, addresses, officers, and employees in North Carolina.
    - Textiles, 1956-1962, 1967and undated (Box 179, Folder 1-6)
    - Textiles and Cotton, 1957-1962and undated (Box 180, Folder 1-2)
    - Miscellany, 1956-1965 (Box 180, Folder 3)
- House of Representatives Series, 1963-1968and undated,primarily 1965-1968
  In this series is information concerning miscellaneous pieces of legislation generally not related to Whitener's Judiciary Committee and District of Columbia Committee work. Most of these bills were introduced by Whitener. There was little apparent order to the folders, so they were organized into two major files: Legislative Bills and Subject Files for Legislation, etc.
  - Legislative Bills
    In this section are folders for various House of Representatives Bills, as well as for a few resolutions, and a Senate bill. This bill (S. 2658) related to vehicle weight and width limitations on the Interstate system. There are several folders pertaining to this bill, which are primarily constituent letters from May to July, 1968. Folders usually contain a copy of the bill, and often printed reports, correspondence, and other background information. Arrangement of the folders is by Congress and session, and by specific bill (H.R.) number; they run from the 89th Congress, 1st Session, 1965 to the 90th Congress, 2nd Session, 1968. A comprehensive listing of the title and number off each bill in this category is filed in folder one of the first box of the Legislative Bills files.
    - 89th Congress, 1st Session, 1965 (Box 181, Folder 2-17)
    - 89th Congress, 2nd Session, 1966 (Box 181, Folder 18-22)
    - 90th Congress, 1st Session, 1967 (Box 182, Folder 1-8)
    - 90th Congress, 2nd Session 1968
      - H. Res. 1200 - S. 2658 (1968, Apr. - May) (Box 182, Folder 9-14)
      - S. 2658 (1968, June- July) (Box 183, Folder 1-4)
    - Bills introduced by Whitener during the 88th Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1963-l964. (Box 183, Folder 5)
  - Subject Files for Legislation, Etc.
    Included is a major section entitled, Gun Control Legislation, which comprises approximately one-half of this series.
    - Gun Control Legislation, 1966-1968(mostly 1968, June)
      The Majority of the material in the Gun Control Legislation section consists of letters from Whitener's constituents and from other persons interested in this legislation. Most of the North Carolina correspondence seems to be in opposition to such gun control bills as S.3604, S. 3605, and H.R. 17735, although the responses from non-North Carolina residents contained more mixed attitudes. Additionally there are letters from some government officials as well as printed material.
      - Tenth Congressional District
        - Papers, 1968, June (Box 184, Folder 1-4)
        - Papers, 1968, July (Box 185, Folder 1-2)
      - North Carolina, Outside Tenth Congressional District
        - Papers, 1968, Apr.,June (Box 185, Folder 3-4)
        - Papers, Julyand undated (Box 186, Folder 1)
      - Outside North Carolina
        - Papers, 1965-1968,June (Box 186, Folder 2-5)
        - Papers, 1968, Julyand undated (Box 187, Folder 1-2)
      - Miscellany, 1966-1968 (Box 187, Folder 3)
    - Social Security Bill, 1968 (Box 187, Folder 4)
    - Miscellany, 1963-1968and undated (Box 187, Folder 5)
- Military and Veterans Series, 1945-1968
  There are two major categories included in this series: the Military and Veterans Files, and Subject Files. The Military and Veterans Files span the 81st Congress, 2nd Session, 1950, through the 90th Congress, 2nd Session, 1968. Please note that in the Congressional office the military files and veterans files were kept separate through the 86th Congress, but that beginning with the 87th Congress, these files were combined. This arrangement has been retained. Also note that the early files, the 81st through the 84th Congresses, are the papers of Woodrow Wilson Jones, Whitener's predecessor in office. Congressman Jones was elected to the 81st Congress to fill a vacancy and was reelected to the 82nd, 83rd and 84th Congresses, thus serving from Nov. 7, 1950, to Jan. 3, 1957.
  The Military and Veterans Files primarily consist of correspondence between Jones or Whitener and their constituents. Generally, all correspondence for persons whose last name begins with the same letter of the alphabet has been kept together under that letter. Occasional folders appear for single individuals. These files originally formed a large part of the office files of Jones and Whitener. The military records, for persons still on active duty or in the reserves, pertain to such matters as requests for transfers, reassignments, allotments, hardship discharges, deferments, and dependents to go overseas. Constituents also wrote concerning courts-martial, Officer Candidate School applications, AWOL soldiers, and efforts to locate a soldier. The veterans records include letters concerning dependency allowances, widow pension benefits, hospitalization benefits, insurance, disability claims, and appeals to the Board of Veterans Appeals. Since these papers are very routine, concerning individual benefits and requests, rather than being topical in nature, only a representative sample has been retained. The letter C, a large letter which includes a wide range of ethnic groups, was chosen for retention, as well as a few small subject folders.
  - Military and Veterans Files
    - Military: 81st Congress, 2nd Session, 1950and 82nd Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1951-1952
      - Air Force ROTC (Box 188, Folder 1)
      - Bridgeman, Edgar R. (Box 188, Folder 2)
      - C (Box 188, Folder 3)
      - 311th Station Hospital (Box 188, Folder 4)
    - Veterans: 81st Congress, 2nd Session, 1950and 82nd Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1951-1952
      - C (Box 188, Folder 5)
      - Carpenter, Eugene (Box 188, Folder 6)
      - Carver, William M. (Box 188, Folder 7)
      - Champion, Flay O. (Box 188, Folder 8)
      - Crosby, Floyd L. (Box 188, Folder 9)
      - G. I. Loans (Box 188, Folder 10)
    - Military: 83rd Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1953-1954
      - Navy Department (Box 188, Folder 12)
      - Prisoners of War Claims (Box 188, Folder 13)
    - Veterans: 83rd Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1953-1954
      - C (Box 188, Folder 14)
      - Veterans, Korean (Box 188, Folder 15)
        Mimeographed letters from veterans, urging [whitener] to use his influence in an effort to keep the subsistence pay of the Korean veterans, taking training under public law 550, the same throughout the training period.
    - Military: 84th Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1955-1956
      - Air Force Department (Box 188, Folder 16)
      - C (Box 188, Folder 17)
      - Corps of Engineers (Box 188, Folder 18)
    - Veterans: 84th Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1955-1956
      - C (Box 189, Folder 1)
    - Military: 85th Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1957-1958
      - Air Force Academy Athletic Association (Box 189, Folder 2)
      - C (Box 189, Folder 3)
    - Veterans: 85th Congress, 1st and 2nd Session, 1957-1958
      - C (Box 189, Folder 4)
      - Carlton, Russell R. (Box 189, Folder 5)
    - Military: 86th Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1959-1960
      - Army (Box 189, Folder 6)
      - C (Box 189, Folder 7)
    - Veterans: 86th Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1959-1960
      - C (Box 189, Folder 8)
    - Military and Veterans: 87th Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1961-1962
      - Army and Navy Departments (Box 189, Folder 9)
      - C (Box 189, Folder 10-11)
      - Veterans, General (Box 189, Folder 12)
      - Veterans Pension Legislation - Constituent mail in1962concerning this legislation. (Box 190, Folder 1-2)
    - Military and Veterans: 88th Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1963-1964
      - Allotments (Box 190, Folder 3)
      - Air Force, Army, and Navy Departments (Box 190, Folder 4)
      - C (Box 190, Folder 5-7)
    - Military and Veterans: 89th Congress, 1st and 2nd Sessions, 1965-1966
      - See Office Files Series: Military and Veterans for the C file. (Box 190)
      - Military, General - Memoranda, policies and procedures, and forms. (Box 191, Folder 1)
    - Military and Veterans: 90th Congress, 1st Session, 1967
      - C (Box 191, Folder 2-4)
      - Clary, Landrum, 1965-1967 (Box 191, Folder 5)
      - Navy Department (Box 191, Folder 6)
    - Military and Veterans: 90th Congress, 2nd Session, 1968
      - C (Box 192, Folder 1-5)
  - Subject Files
    - Committee on Veterans' Affairs, House of Representatives, 1957 (Box 193, Folder 1)
      Printed letters to Congressman Olin E. Teague, Chairman of the committee, from various government officials, such as Joseph Campbell, Comptroller General of the United States. Included are several House bills.
    - Insurance, Reinstatement of, 1957-1958 (Box 193, Folder 2)
    - Veterans Administration, 1945-1959and undated (Box 193, Folder 3-4)
      Primarily mimeographed information about the Veterans Administration and VA hospitals, as well as; VA Information Service press releases, application forms, etc.
    - Veterans Affairs, 1952, 1956-1957
      - General Correspondence, A-Z (Box 193, Folder 5-23)
        Concerns such matters as the interest rate for VA loans, site for a VA hospital, VA home mortgages, and Committee on Veterans' Affairs information. The H file contains Treasury and Post Office appropriation information.
      - Veterans Legislation, 1958and undated (Box 193, Folder 24)
        Constituent mail supporting various veterans bills being considered by the House of Representatives.
- Military Academy Series, 1958-1968
  In this series is general information about the U. S. military academies: the Air Force Academy, Coast Guard Academy, Merchant Marine Academy, Military Academy at West Point, and Naval Academy. Included are materials such as pamphlets describing the academies, guidelines for Congressmen in appointing candidates to vacancies, and information concerning entrance examinations. The majority of this series has been discarded because it consisted of individual application materials and academic records of Whitener's appointees. Representative items were grade transcripts, letters of recommendation, biographical data, medical records, and academy entrance examination results. The Buckley Amendment of 1967 to the Privacy Act prohibits the use of such materials without the individual's written consent.
  - U.S. Air Force Academy, 1962-1968 (Box 194, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Coast Guard Academy, 1958-1968 (Box 194, Folder 2-3)
  - U.S. Merchant Marine Academy, 1959-1968 (Box 194, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Military Academy, West Point, 1962-1968 (Box 194, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Naval Academy, 1961-1968 (Box 194, Folder 6)
  - Miscellany, 1963-1968 (Box 194, Folder 7)
- Trips Series, 1944-1968,primarily 1959-1968
  Information pertaining to a sequence of journeys that Whitener took, primarily in his official capacity as a congressman, comprises this series. The trips, from 1959 to 1968, included travels within the United States, as well as to Europe, the Far East, and South Vietnam. Included are correspondence; fact sheets, illustrated brochures, and other information concerning countries visited; press kits; speeches Whitener made; briefing material; Whitener's personal notes; and printed material. There are a number of pictures taken on the Far East Trip, Captive Nations Week trip, and Vietnam trips.
  - Air Force Trip, 1963
    A delegation of North Carolina businessmen, accompanied by Whitener and his Administrative Assistant, Herbert M. Lineberger, attended a commando demonstration et the Special Air Warfare Center (SAWC) at Eglin Air Force Base on October 8, 1963.
    - Papers, 1963, July-Oct. (Box 195, Folder 1)
  - Air Force Trip, 1964
    Tour of North Carolina business executives in June, 1964,to visit headquarters of SAC in Omaha, Nebraska; NORAD in Colorado Springs, Colorado; and the U.S. Air Force Academy.
    - Papers, 1964, Mar.-July (Box 195, Folder 2)
    - Personal Histories of Businessmen, undated (Box 195, Folder 3)
  - Air Force Trip, 1965
    Proposed Air Force Systems Command tour by a party of North Carolina businessmen inOct., 1965.
    - Papers, 1965, Jan.-July (Box 195, Folder 4)
  - Air Force Trip, 1968
    Whitener escorted a group of about twenty-five young North Carolina businessmen on a visit to the Special Air Warfare Center (SAWC) at Eglin Air Force Base, to witness a demonstration of air power at MacDill Air Force Base, and to tour Cape Kennedy, on January 18-19, 1968.
    - Papers, 1967, Nov.-1968, Mar. (Box 195, Folder 5)
  - Captive Nations Week Trip, 1967
    Concerns a week of speeches and meetings sponsored by the Asian Peoples' Anti-Communist League, during July 16-22, 1967. The activities, which took place in Taipei, Taiwan, included the annual plenary meeting on July 20 of the China Chapter of the Asian Peoples' Anti-Communist League, at which Whitener delivered a lecture. Whitener was also the featured speaker at a mass rally on July 22. Included in the folders are such items as press releases, newspaper stories, correspondence, and pictures.
    - Papers, 1967, Feb.-Oct.and undated (Box 196, Folder 1-5)
    - Pictures,1967 (Box 196, Folder 6)
  - European Trip, 1959
    Whitener travelled to Europe, February 4-16, 1959, as a member of the House Committee on the Judiciary to investigate matters within the jurisdiction of the committee. His itinerary included stops in London, the Hague, Paris, and Berlin. Included are maps, itineraries, passport and travel information, and other tourist information concerning Europe. There is printed information about Parliament, a County Court Handbook (1959, London), and material relating to the International Criminal Police Organization (INTERPOL). Also, Whitener wrote personal reports and memoranda concerning the trip.
    - Papers, 1944-1960and undated (Box 197, Folder 1-7)
    - Papers, undated (Box 198, Folder 1)
    - Printed Material (Box 198, Folder 2-3)
    - Financial Papers (Box 198, Folder 4)
  - Far East Trip, 1961
    Whitener evidently made this visit in March and April, 1961, as a member of the Immigration Subcommittee, Committee on the Judiciary, House of Representatives. The other members of the delegation were Arch A. Moore, Jr., Chairman and Representative from West Virginia, and William Crabtree, Committee Staff member. They made stops in Honolulu, Hong Kong, and Tokyo.
    - Papers, 1961, Mar.-Juneand undated (Box 198, Folder 5)
  - Far East Trip, 1965
    This journey was officially named the North Carolina Business Executives Trade Study Mission. The trip was from October 24 to November 8, 1965, and the itinerary included stops in Honolulu, Tokyo, Taipei, Hong Kong, Bankok, and Manila. Included are printed brochures and other information about the countries the group visited, such as briefing material, and press and visitors kits.
    - Papers, 1962, Nov.-1965, Sept. (Box 198, Folder 6-7)
    - Papers, 1965, Oct.-1966, Oct. (Box 199, Folder 1-5)
    - Papers, undated (Box 200, Folder 1-4)
    - Pictures (Box 200, Folder 5)
  - Vietnam Trip, 1966